Guide to the Brooklyn clubs collection ARC.172
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn clubs collection
1843-2016
1860-1950
Brooklyn Historical Society
ARC.172
4.25 Linear Feet in nine manuscript boxes and two oversize folders.
The Brooklyn clubs collection includes varied organizations from political, to professional, to social. Materials represented in the collection include yearbooks, event programs, constitutions and bylaws, newsletters, bulletins, membership lists, calendars, annual reports, and printed ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source and date of acquisition for the majority of the collection are unknown. When known, the information is noted at the folder level.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by club name.
Historical note
Political clubs were among the earliest clubs to be organized in New York City. In the 1760s, along with pre-revolutionary rumblings in America, political clubs formed in support of the colonists or the loyalists. Following the American Revolutionary War, political clubs were established to support newly formed political parties, chiefly the Democratic Republicans and the Federalists. During the 19th century, as the idea of civic responsibility grew among citizens, so did the establishment of political clubs. Political clubs could be small and localized such as those that were organized within wards (small political units in New York City representing a geographic area within the city) or large city-wide political clubs. By the 1850s, political clubs had much influence over the city; the outcome of elections was often decided by strong voter turn out from political club members.
Following the American Civil War, political clubs began to loose clout, and by the end of the 19th century, many citizens had turned to social clubs to affect civic reform. Social clubs were also being established solely for pleasure, camaraderie, and personal growth. In the 1830s, New York City had only three social clubs (the Union Club; the Hone Club; and the Kent Club). In the last quarter of the 19th century, New York City had more social clubs than any other city the world, with the exception of London. This period also saw the formation of university clubs, athletic clubs, women's clubs, and professional clubs, among others.
Several factors led to the demise of many social clubs, chiefly the invention of the automobile and its effect on how and where people lived (for example, the growth of suburbs), the financial fallout following a series of economic depressions in the United States in the 1890s through the 1930s, and the establishment of anti-discrimination laws that, in part, addressed the exclusionary practices so many social clubs held. In the 1950s and 1960s, neighborhood social clubs flourished within local immigrant populations in New York City, many of which are still active today.
Sources:
Gronowicz, Anthony. "Political clubs." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson, 1011-1012. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 2010.
Mooney, James E. "Social clubs." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson, 1197. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 2010.
Blair, Karen J. "Women's clubs." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson, 1407-1408. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 2010.
Mooney, James E. and Kenneth T. Jackson. "University clubs." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson, 1351. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 2010.
Related Materials
Apollo Club of Brooklyn programs, 1886 – 1967 (ARC.144)
Atlantic Yacht Club publications, 1866 – 1891 (ARC.140)
Brooklyn animal welfare organizations collection, 1868 – 1903 (ARC.151)
Brooklyn Arts and Culture Association publications, 1969 – 1997 (ARC.149)
Brooklyn Engineers' Club publications, 1897 – 1973 (ARC.156)
Brooklyn Heights Association collection, 1929 – 1998 (ARC.148)
Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations collection, 1829 – 1998 (ARC.141)
Brooklyn League annual reports and publications, 1902 – 1912 (ARC.159)
Brooklyn newsletter collection, 1869 - 2004 (ARC.174)
Brooklyn Woman's Club yearbooks, 1903 – 1943 (ARC.158)
Brooklyn YMCA Central Branch publications, 1884 – 1967 (ARC.169)
Chiropean yearbooks, 1911 – 1965 (ARC.164)
Crescent Athletic Club yearbooks and bulletins, 1891 – 1940 (ARC.178)
Fraternal organizations of Brooklyn collection, 1845 – 1997 (ARC.147)
Kings County Chapter of the New York State Society of Professional Engineers publications, 1940 – 1966 (ARC.146)
Rotary Club of Brooklyn publications, 1919 – 1977 (ARC.143)
Third Kings Masonic Camp Fund publications, 1937 – 1987 (ARC.162)
Union League Club of Brooklyn yearbooks, 1890 – 1912 (ARC.157)
Scope and Contents
Clubs represented in the collection are varied, with interests ranging from political, to professional, to social. Materials represented in the collection include yearbooks, event programs, constitutions and bylaws, certificates of membership, newsletters, bulletins, membership lists, calendars, annual reports, and printed ephemera.
The yearbooks are of particular interest as they often include membership lists, names of officers and committee members, constitutions and bylaws, articles of incorporation, and historical information pertaining to the club.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Bylaws (administrative records); Articles of incorporation; Newsletters; Clippings (information artifacts); Membership lists; Automobiles -- Societies, etc.; Art -- Societies, etc.; Library clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Riding clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Science clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Literature -- Societies, etc.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Constitutions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 19th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Societies -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Societies and clubs; Choral societies -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Political clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Athletic clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Private clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sailing clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Yearbooks; Annual reports; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Midwood (New York, N.Y.); Ridgewood (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Concord Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Conchological Club; Cambridge Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Athletic Association; Brooklyn Barnard Club; Brooklyn Chautauqua Union (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Chorus (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Club (New York, N.Y.); Franklin Literary Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Friendly Tourists' Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Hanover Club of Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Heights Casino (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Saengerbund (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Republican Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Photographic Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Horticultural Society; Kings County Civil Employees Benevolent Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Invincible Club (New York, N.Y.); Lawyers' Club of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Kosmos Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Long Island Automobile Club of Brooklyn; Lincoln Club (New York, N.Y.); Dramatic Readers (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Entre Nous Dramatic and Literary Association; Democratic Union Association (New York, N.Y.); Democratic Union General Committee of the City of Brooklyn and County of Kings (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Democratic Union Party of the City of Brooklyn and County of Kings (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Daughters of the American Revolution. Fort Greene Chapter (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); National Society, Colonial Daughters of the Seventeenth Century; Junior League of Brooklyn; United War Veterans of Kings County; New Utrecht Liberty Pole Association; 12:30 Club of Bay Ridge, Inc; Twelve Fifteen Club of South Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Italian Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Tree Planting and Fountain Society of Brooklyn; Republican Party (Kings County, N.Y.). General Committee; Turn-Verein Vorwärts (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Brooklyn Club; Tenth Ward Democratic Buchanan Keystone Club of the City of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Indian Amateur League of Brooklyn; Ridgewood Household Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Rembrandt Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Society of Old Brooklynites (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Riding and Driving Club of Brooklyn; Monday Club of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Midwood Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Prospect Club (Park Slope, New York, N.Y.); Philharmonic Society of Brooklyn; Long Island Library Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Long Island Bottlers' Union (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Merchants' Association of New York; Marine and Field Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Musaeola Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Neurological Society; Municipal Club of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Oxford Club of Brooklyn; New York State Association Opposed to Woman Suffrage. Brooklyn Auxiliary; Women's Christian Temperance Union on the Hill (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Yacht Racing Association of Gravesend Bay; Winter's Night Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Women's Bar Association; Twenty-first Ward Republican Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Twentieth Century Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Co-Operative Colonization Society; Brooklyn Yacht Club; A Cappella Singers (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Alcyone Boat Club; American Institute of Architects. Brooklyn Chapter; American Institute of Bank Clerks. Brooklyn Chapter; Arion Ladies Chorus (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Arion Singing Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Asacog Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Aquarium Society; Brooklyn Catholic Oratorio Society; Booth Dramatic Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Sea Scouts (Boy Scouts of America); Federal Republican Club of Kings County
- The A Cappella Singers of the Ridgewood Art Center, 1940 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  One concert program, 1940.
- Alcyone Boat Club, 1869-1890 (Box 1)
  Constitution and by-laws, 1869-1890.
- American Institute of Architects, Brooklyn chapter, 1908-1975 (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1908, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Pylon newsletter, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
- American Institute of Bank Clerks, Brooklyn chapter, 1904 (Box 1)
  One event program publication that includes Articles of Association, member information and photographs, a history of the chapter, advertisements and more.
- Arion Ladies' Chorus, 1943-1958 (Box 1)
  Three anniversary programs from 1943, 1953, and 1958.
- Arion Singing Society, 1935-1965 (Box 1)
  Three concert programs from 1935, 1937, and 1965.
- Asacog Club of Brooklyn, 1901-1902 (Box 1)
  Two yearbooks, 1901 and 1902.
- Booth Dramatic Society, 1893 (Box 1)
  One program, 1893.
- Boy Scouts of America, Brooklyn Council, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks and reports, 1929, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Scout Camps booklets, 1930-1937 (Box 1)
  - University of Scouting pamphlets, circa 1930s (Box 1)
  - Ephemera, circa 1930s (Box 1)
    Christmas card and coupon sheet.
  - Constitution, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
  - Council Ring newsletter, 1931-1937 (Box 1)
  - Event programs, 1935-36, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Joseph Nichols materials, 1928-1941 (Box 1)
    Membership card, 1928; letter and certificate, 1941.
- Brooklyn Aquarium Society, 1918 (Box 1)
  The Aquarium Bulletin, May 1918.
- Brooklyn Athletic Association, circa 1886 (Box 1)
  Winter Meeting program, circa 1886.
- Brooklyn Barnard Club, 1897-1903 (Box 2)
  Yearbooks, 1897, 1898, 1901, 1903.
- Brooklyn Catholic Oratorio Society, 1910 (Box 2)
  Concert program, 1910.
- Brooklyn Chautauqua Union, 1897 (Box 2)
  Yearbook, 1897.
- The Brooklyn Chorus, 1910 (Box 2)
- The Brooklyn Club, 1866-1991 (Box 2)
  - Yearbooks, 1866-1927 (Box 2)
  - Event programs and menus, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Member lists, 1895-1991 (Box 2)
  - Constitution and by-laws, circa 1940s (Box 2)
  - Brooklyn Club News newsletter, 1944, 1959 (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Conchological Club, 1907 (Box 2)
  Bulletin, 1907.
- Brooklyn Concord Club, 1956 (Box 2)
  Brooklyn Concord Democrat newsletter, November 1956.
- Brooklyn Co-operative Colonization Society, circa 1878-1880 (Box 2)
  Constitution and documents, circa 1878-1880.
- Brooklyn Horticultural Society, 1857-1864 (Box 2)
  Annual report, 1857; constitution and by-laws, 1858; exhibition tickets and rules, 1858-1864; news clippings.
- Brooklyn Photographic Society, 1894 (Box 2)
  Constitution, by-laws, and member list, 1864.
- Brooklyn Republican Club, 1893 (Box 2)
  Yearbook, 1893.
- Brooklyn Saengerbund, 1909-1930 (Box 2)
  Biographical / Historical
  German-American singing society.
  - Mitglieder-Liste [member lists], 1909-1930 (Box 2)
  - Jahres-Berichte [annual reports], 1911-1918 (Box 2)
  - Event programs, 1912-1918 (Box 2)
    Trip to Germany, 1912; Carneval, 1918.
- Brooklyn Women's Bar Association, circa 2005-2018 (Box 3)
  Various texts on the association's history.
- Brooklyn Yacht Club, 1872 (Box 3)
  Regatta program, 1872.
- Cambridge Club, 1891-1944 (Box 3)
  - Yearbooks, 1891-1939 (Box 3)
  - Event program, 1915 (Box 3)
  - Calendars, 1902-1944 (Box 3)
  - A History of the Cambridge Club, 1911 (Box 3)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Mrs. William C. Richardson.
    Written by May Ellis Nichols. Also available on the library shelves (call number 367 N).
- Colonial Daughters of the 17th Century, 1927-1936 (Box 3)
  Member lists and addenda, 1933-1936; event program, 1927.
- Daughters of the American Revolution, Fort Greene chapter, 1921-1929 (Box 3)
  Member lists, 1921-1928; charter, 1929.
- Democratic Union General Committee of the City of Brooklyn, 1861 (Box 3)
  Constitution and by-laws, 1861.
- Democratic Union Party of the City of Brooklyn, 1861 (Box 3)
  Constitution, 1861.
- Dramatic Readers, 1944-1948 (Box 3)
  Formerly owned by Alice G. Fell.
  Constitution and by-laws, 1944; yearbooks, 1945-1948.
- Dudley Buck Quartet Club, 1885 (Box 3)
  Concert program, 1885.
- Entre Nous Dramatic and Literary Association of Brooklyn, 1871 (Box 3)
  Constitution and by-laws, 1871.
- Federal Republican Club of Kings County, 1938 (Box 3)
  50th anniversary program, 1938.
- Franklin Literary Society, 1843-1884 (Box 3)
  Constitution and by-laws, 1843; Manuals, 1878 and 1884.
- Friendly Tourist Club of Brooklyn, 1914-1944 (Box 4)
  Constitution and by-laws, 1925 and 1941; programs, 1914-1944.
- George H. Nichols Regular Republican Organization, 9th A.D., Kings County, 1955 (Box 4)
  Event program, 1955.
- Hanover Club of Brooklyn, 1900-1913 (Box 4)
  Yearbooks, 1900 and 1913.
- The Heights Casino, 1905-2004 (Box 4)
  A racquet sports club in Brooklyn Heights.
  - Yearbooks, 1905-1963 (Box 4)
  - Heights Casino Monthly newsletter, 1953 (Box 4)
- Indian Amateur League of Brooklyn, 1903-1904 (Box 4)
  Programs, including for the Seminole Athletic Club, 1903-1904.
- Invincible Club of Brooklyn, 1901 (Box 4)
  Constitution and by-laws, 1901.
- Italian Historical Society, 1971 (Box 4)
  Columbus Day program, 1971.
- Junior League of Brooklyn, 1930, 1960 (Box 4)
  Programs and clippings related to the League's reproduction of the 1864 Sanitary Fair, 1930; event programs from the League's Golden Anniversary (1960) and Hemisphere Ball (1962).
- Kings County Civil Employees Benevolent Association, 1922-1923 (Box 4)
  Bulletin, 1922-1923.
- Kings County Republican County Committee, 1955-1965 (Box 4, Box OS-32)
  Lincoln Dinner materials, 1955-1965.
- Kosmos Club, 1927-1941 (Box 4)
  Constitution and by-laws, 19227 and 1928; yearbooks, 1932-1941.
- The Lawyers' Club of Brooklyn, 1922-1954 (Box 5)
  Yearbooks, 1922-1923 and 1953-1954.
- The Lincoln Club, 1900 (Box 5)
  Yearbook, 1900.
- The Long Island Automobile Club, 1912 (Box 5)
  Yearbook, 1912.
- Long Island Bottlers' Union, 1900 (Box 5)
  By-laws, 1900.
- Long Island Library Club, 1904, 1912 (Box 5)
  Constitution, officers and membership lists, 1904 and 1912.
- The Marine and Field Club, 1887-1903 (Box 5)
  Located in Bath Beach. Yearbooks, 1894, 1897, 1903; program and menu, 1887; club house memo, 1895.
- Merchants' Association, 1928-1929 (Box 5)
  Greater New York newsletter, 1928-1929.
- Midwood Club, circa 1890 (Box 5)
  Related Materials
  Adrian Vanderveer Martense collection (ARC.191)
  Scrapbook, circa 1890. "Newspaper clippings, circulars, etc., relating to the Midwood Club, Flatbush, Long Island. Collected by Adrian V. Martense."
- The Monday Club of Brooklyn, 1914 (Box 5)
  Yearbook, 1914.
- Montauk Club, 1889-2008 (Box 5)
  The 1894 yearbook was the gift of Paul Maddaus.
  Yearbooks, 1889-1924; brochures, circa 2008.
- The Municipal Club of Brooklyn, 1899-2016 (Box 6)
  Yearbooks, 1918-1935 and 1988-2016; Bulletin, 1899.
- Musaeola Association, 1864 (Box 6)
  Constitution, by-laws, and membership list, 1864.
- National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Club, Inc., Brooklyn Club, 1973 (Box 6)
  Gift of Lewis W. Francis, Jr.
  Event program, 1973. Includes a profile of Eubie Blake, recipient of the Association's Professional Award.
- Neurological Society, 1920 (Box 6)
  Member list, 1920.
- New Utrecht Liberty Pole Association, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 6)
  Gift of Miss Frances Cropsey.
  Pamphlet, circa 1940s-1950s.
- New York State Association Opposed to Woman Suffrage, Brooklyn Auxiliary, circa 1908 (Box 6)
  Pamphlet and literature, circa 1908.
- Oxford Club of Brooklyn, 1887-1890 (Box 6)
  Yearbooks, 1887-1890.
- Parkway Driving Club, circa late 19th-early 20th century (Box 6)
  One admission ticket.
- Philharmonic Society of Brooklyn, 1857-1890 (Box 6)
  - Annual reports, 1857-1864 (Box 6)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1857 (Box 6)
  - Concert programs, 1857-1890 (Box 6)
  - Ephemera, 1857-1861 (Box 6)
- Prospect Club, 1900, 1916 (Box 6)
  Yearbook, 1900; constitution and by-laws, 1916.
- Rembrandt Club, 1885-1980 (Box 7)
  Constitutions, yearbooks and member lists, 1885-1980.
- Ridgewood Household Club, 1901-1902 (Box 7)
  First annual report, 1901-1902.
- The Riding and Driving Club of Brooklyn, 1893-1927 (Box 7)
  Yearbooks, 1896-1927; horse show programs, 1893-1895.
- Society of Old Brooklynites, 1880-1924 (Box 7, Box OS-38)
  Yearbooks, 1880, 1887, 1924; event materials, 1886-1973; undated oversize Washington Roebling poster.
- Tenth Ward Democratic Buchanan Keystone Club, 1856 (Box 7)
  Constitution and by-laws, 1856.
- The Tree Planting and Fountain Society of Brooklyn, 1890-1898 (Box 8)
  - Yearbook, 1890 (Box 8)
  - Annual reports, 1896-1898 (Box 8)
  - Bulletins, 1894-1895 (Box 8)
  - Circulars, 1897 (Box 8)
- Turn-Verein of Brooklyn, 1937-1939 (Box 8)
  Turner-Topics newsletter, 1937; member list, 1939.
- 12:15 Club of South Brooklyn, 1934-1961 (Box 8)
  Bound volumes were the gift of Ella Robinson.
  Bound volumes of Spotlight newsletter, vols. 1-15, 1934-1950; Loose issues, January 1961.
- 12:30 Club of Bay Ridge, 1957 (Box 8)
  High Noon newsletter, September 1957.
- Twentieth Century Club of New York City, 1896-1927 (Box 8)
  Yearbooks 1896-1927 and one visitors' register from an 1897 reception to Dr. Fridtjof Nansen.
- Twenty-first Ward Republican Association, 1887 (Box 9)
  By-laws.
- United War Veterans of Kings County, 1948-1967 (Box 9)
  Memorial Day Parade programs.
- Winter's Night Club, 1918-1927 (Box 9)
  Yearbooks, member lists, and documents.
- Women's Christian Temperance Union, Brooklyn, 1881 (Box 9)
  First annual report.
- Yacht Racing Association of Gravesend Bay, 1913-1914 (Box 9)
  By-laws, yearbook and racing rules.